Okay, good morning. We are doing Mesopotamia today.
好的，早上好。今天我们来讲古巴比伦。
This is the Bronze Age.
这是古代金属时代。
We did Egypt last class.
我们上节课做了古埃及。
We are doing Mesopotamia today. In the next class, we will finish with the Indus Valley.
我们今天要讲古巴比伦。
So, before I begin,
I want to make three general points about the study of history
...
and how civilizations develop.
和……以………
The first point is this.
??
Every culture has a mythology.
每个文化都有神话。
And the mythology is the
collective worldview of the people
集体的世界观
that lets them understand the reality around them.
让它们能理解周围的现实
So another idea that
又一条想法是，是共享的
we can say is mythology is a shared reality.
又一条想法，可说是
And every civilization has mythology.
...
So, for example,
today our mythology would be science
...
and history, right?
??
We think they are true and objective,
我们认为它们是...
but they're actually mythologies.
They're a shared reality. And
它们是...
every civilization would have its own mythology.
every civilization wouldhave its own mythology.
And that's what makes the culture unique.
...
Okay? So that's the first point. So
OK?
what we will do today to better understand Mesopotamia is to compare
and contrast its mythology with that of the Egyptians.
和...对比...
Okay? Second point is
OK
there's an idea called the dialectic. And
...
this was an idea proposed by the German philosopher named Frederick Hegel in the 19th century.
He believes that
...
history is driven by opposing ideas.
历史由对立思想驱动。
So whenever you have one mythology or one idea,
历史总能出现两种相对的思路。
there always must arise another opposing idea
有时必有另一种对立思想
that challenges it.
有点儿…
And that's what drives history.
而这就是推动历史的力量。
And history is always moving towards a synthesis of ideas.
历史总是向着思想的合成前进。
Okay? So the example would be there's capitalism,
好的？所以例子就是资本主义，而对立的想法是共产主义。
and the opposing idea would be communism.
好的，先前的例子是…
And the synthesis of the idea would be socialism.
...
Okay? And what's really important to understand
is that ideas can be living things
是的，想法可以是活着的事物
that change over time.
是的...
The third idea I want to introduce is the
第3个...????????????????????????????????????????????????????
idea of diversity and differentiation.
]}We need to translate cues 43-45. They are two cues: [43] The third idea... [44] idea of diversity... [45] And the idea here is. Actually cues 43-45 are three lines? Wait: [43] The third idea I want tointroduce is the [44] idea of diversity and differentiation. [45] And the idea here is. So we need to produce translations array with three strings. Use Chinese. Use line breaks if needed. Let's produce:
And the idea here is
]? Wait we need to produce JSON with translations array. Each string may contain newline. Let's produce: [
we humans have some fundamental natures about us.
]}We need to translate 1 cue?Wait? The last cue? Let's…..??
So for example, we're all religious in some aspect.
So for example, we're allreligious in some aspect.
Another fundamental
...
instinct about us, we strive to be different.
??
And that's why diversity is the iron law of society.
]}We need to translate? The last cue? ...? .....……………..………..……..……………………………………………………………………………??..??..??………………..…….....?…..…………………………..……..…………………………………………………………………………………
Okay? So the example is in a family,
??
all the siblings will be different.
all ... ?? ?? 兄 ?? ? ? ? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ………?? ? ? ?? 兄 ..??…………………………………………………………………………………
In a classroom, the students will be different.
在一个课堂里，学生们会有不同的表现
And you could be a certain way in a classroom,
...
and then you go to another classroom
??
and you figure out the students there are similar to you,
so you will change as a person to differentiate yourself from other people.
所以你会像个体会变成…
Okay? So that's also another principle of history.
...
Societies strive to be different from each other.
社会努力彼此区别。
They strive for diversity and differentiation.
他们追求多样性与差异。
We cannot make generalizations about societies.
我们可以做出…
The only thing that we can say is
?
societies or cultures fall into a spectrum.
???
Okay? And
?
they're usually defined by
它们通常由...
the elite or generalizations.
它们的...
So this is another way of saying today I'm
67: So this is..???
going to make very broad generalizations about these societies
?
and generalizations. And
和一般化。和
they're useful for our purposes,
它们的...
but I want you to be aware that
these are simplifications, these are generalizations.
???
Okay? Alright.
]}
So let's start.
?
Okay. So
好的。于是
Mesopotamia is a very different culture
美索波特米亚是一个与埃及的地理位置相差的文化与文明。
and civilization than Egypt because of its geography.
Okay? So if you look at the geography of Egypt,
好的？于是如果你看埃及的地理位置，
it has natural boundaries.
它有自然界限。
So for example, to the
于是可是有点儿…
west is the Sahara Desert.
西边是撒哈拉沙漠。
To the north is the Mediterranean Sea.
北边是地中海。
To the east is the Red Sea.
东边是红海。
Okay? And then to the south are the Cataracts.
好的？然后南边是尼罗河的落差。
So it makes it hard to travel up the Nile
它给了我方位的好处！
from the south.
此时…
So there are really only two access points into Egypt,
有两条通往埃及的路，
which can be easily defended.
可归一条可归一条…
The south and also from the Levant,
{
which is basically Israel, Syria, Jordan.
哪一条是基本上是以色列、叙利安、约旦的组合。
And because of its natural boundaries,
而且因其自然界线，埃及方可归一条…
Egypt doesn't really feel threatened by external enemies,
埃及不再给我方位…
right? Also, it has the Nile River,
右吗？另外，河流有河流…
which is the foundation of its civilization.
...
Remember last class we talked about how the Nile was very generous.
It flooded predictably every season,
它在每个季节里都能自发洪水，
and so it made agriculture very productive
它在每个前景里…
in Egypt, which
他在…
allowed them to sustain a very large population,
允许他们维持大规模人口，
which then
它们的后续可用来制作…
can be used to create monuments like the pyramid.
其可用…
So for most of its history, Egypt was stable
所以在其历史的大部分里，埃及已相当稳定且相当繁荣。
and prosperous.
米索波特里亚是完全不同的。
Mesopotamia is completely different.
So first of all,
先...??
Mesopotamia, which
??????????????????..??
is in what we call Iraq today,
?..??..???……??
it has no natural boundaries.
...
Mesopotamia is Greek for the land between two rivers.
??
These two rivers are the Euphrates
...
and the Tigris.
和底格里斯河。
To the
To
west of Mesopotamia would be Arabia,
西方的美索不亚是阿拉伯，并且是拉凡特。
and the Levant, okay?
and the Levant,okay?
To the north would be Anatolia.
北方是安纳托利亚。
To the east are the Zagos Mountains.
东边是扎戈斯山脉。
The thing about Anatolia is it
117. 这件事关于安纳托利亚的事，正好…
itself is a very prosperous place.
118. 先前的句子…
So it will become eventually home to certain empires,
[119] 以此为例...
like the Hittites, who
[120] ...
will always threaten Mesopotamia, okay?
将会一直威胁着美索波特米亚，好吗？
So Anatolia is a threat to Mesopotamia.
安纳托利亚是美索波特米亚的威胁。”
The people of Arabia and
阿拉伯人和扎格斯山的人民是…
the Zagos Mountains are nomads.
...………………………………………………
And as we know, nomads are a very aggressive people.
……………………………………………………
And so they will constantly launch raids against Mesopotamia,
和...…
which threatens its safety.
? ?………
Okay? So,
?………
Mesopotamia throughout its history
...
has always been at war with its neighbors.
The other thing about Mesopotamia is,
...
even though it's fertile, it's part of something called a fertile crescent,
即使它很肥沃，它也属于一个叫作“肥沃之弧”的东西，
okay, which extends from Mesopotamia into the Levant, okay?
好的，...从...…
It's called a fertile crescent.
好的…
The Euphrates and the Tigris don't really cooperate.
第1行
They're very chaotic. They change course all the time.
第2行
And so, the only way to tame the Euphrates
第3行
and the Tigris is through irrigation.
和底河的灌溉
Okay? Because if you farm too close to the bed,
好的，先前...
the river bank, you're going to get flooded.
好的
Okay? So they have to develop irrigation in order to tame the Euphrates and the Tigris.
OK? 先前...??
Okay. So, the geography,
??????
all these two cultures are very different,
?
and therefore the history is very different.
和因此，历史非常不同。
For most of its history,
在其大部分历史中，
Egypt was unified as an empire.
埃及已统一为帝国。
It was very stable. But
它很稳定。但
Mesopotamia was always in flux, okay?
美洲在先前...??
So the first great civilization of Mesopotamia were the Sumerians.
它是...
They were eventually conquered by the Akkadians.
他们最终被阿卡德人征服。
And then you have the Assyrians and the Babylonians.
又有亚述人和巴比伦人。
And these four civilizations are what we call Mesopotamia,
这四个文明就是我们所说的美洲。
okay? Okay? Okay, any questions so
好的？好的？好的，先问一下，再说到美洲的简短历史之前。
far before I go into the brief history of Mesopotamia?
好的，先说一说，再把美洲的先前…】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】}】}】?}】?}】?}{
Okay, yeah, that's a good question, okay.
]}??
But what is the relationship between these four relationships?
但这四个文明之间的关系是什么？
The Sumerians, the Akkadians,
苏玛尔人、阿卡德人、巴比伦人和亚述人。
the Babylonians, and the Assyrians.
the Babylonians,and the Assyrians.
Okay, so the very first civilization were the Sumerians.
好的，先说一说…
And then they were eventually united by the Akkadians.
...???????…??……??…???………??……??…………………………………………
Okay, so Sumeria was not really an empire,
??……??……………………………??
it was a culture and a civilization that
它是一种文化和文明，
was divided into city -states, like the Greeks before the conquest of the Macedonians.
它的结构像古希腊的城邦，
And the Akkadians under Sargon of Akkad,
在阿卡德的萨尔贡之下，
or Sargon the Great, united the city -states,
或萨尔贡大帝，统一了城邦，
and gave us the idea of Sumerian civilization.
并给我们呈现了苏美尔文明的概念。
After the Akkadian Empire fell,
在阿卡德帝国落后，
North Mesopotamia became the Assyrian Empire,
北美索波特米亚成为亚述帝国，南美索波特米亚成为巴比伦帝国。
South Mesopotamia became the Babylonian Empire.
他们都把自己视为苏美尔文明的继承者。
They all saw themselves as heirs to the Sumerian civilization.
So even though they're different civilizations,
所以即使它们是不同的文明，
they share a common mythology,
它们有着相同的古典…
okay, which I will discuss later in the class.
先前…
Okay, does that make sense? Great, okay, so
好的，先前…
I'm gonna talk very briefly
OK? 先前…
about how Mesopotamia developed,
OK? 先先…
okay? So, remember
好？所以，记得……
that in the beginning,
OK? 先前…
agriculture first appeared in two places,
??
Anatolia and the Levant, okay?
Then there was something called the
然后有一个叫做的 8.2 千年事件。
8.2 kilo year event.
...
And we can see this as dramatic climate change.
That radically changed the geography
...
and the climate of this world,
??
okay?
And because of the cooling and temperature,
因为降温，黎凡特人和安纳托利亚人被迫扩散。
the people in the Levant, and the people in Anatolia were forced to spread out.
因为降温，黎凡特人和安纳托利】
So they went to Europe, they went to Egypt,
所以他们去了欧洲，去埃及，去美索波特米亚。
they went to Mesopotamia.
And when they did that, they spread agriculture.
}]
And remember, the agriculture, the mythology,
is the mother goddess, which meant that
they were mainly peaceful,
they were mainlypeaceful,
egalitarian people, okay, who were very artistic.
So this is a very peaceful, stable world.
...
But then, you have the 5.9 kilo year event,
year event. This is about 6,000 years ago,
...
4,000 BCE.
199 4,000 BCE.
And again, you saw a radical change
200 ???
in temperature, which
in temperature,which
again forced migration
?
and
和
forced these
被迫
civilizations to change.
205 短语：文明将会改变。
One of the major
206 短语：其中之一是...
changes in Mesopotamia
207. 变化的...??
is the founding of
...
a place called Uruk.
209. 一个叫乌鲁克的地方。
Uruk is interesting because
210. 乌鲁克很有意思，因为它的...
it is considered the first city of the world.
它被认为是世界第一座城市。
And so this is the beginning of what we call civilization,
它们的...
the modern idea of civilization.
这...
And that's about 40,000 people. And
214. 约四万名人。
this is what we consider the beginning of the Sumerian civilization.
215. 这是我们所说的苏美尔文明的起点。
And the Sumerian civilization is considered the cradle of civilization.
216. 苏古里亚文明…
It is the beginning of the foundations of modern civilization.
它是现代文明基础的起点。
They gave us irrigation technology.
他们给我们灌溉技术。
They gave us mathematics.
他们给我们数学。
They gave us astronomy. They gave us writing, cuneiform writing.
他们给我们天文。给我们楔形文字。
They gave us the legal system.
他们给我们法律系统。
They gave us
他们给我们...
hierarchy and religion. So
层级与宗教。于是
there was an explosion of innovation with the founding of Uruk.
“以太空”创立后，出现了创新爆发。
Now Uruk eventually would become a huge city,
“以太空”后期…
which compelled the people to migrate
它们促使人们迁移并建立与乌鲁克相似的城市。
and found cities that are similar to Uruk.
它们是基本上是列岛，分布在中东各处。
They're basically colonies. And they're scattered throughout Mesopotamia.
These are city -states that
...
at first were part of the Uruk civilization.
在第一阶段，乌鲁克文明的初期…
But eventually they became prosperous
...
and wealthy themselves.
和自己富裕。
And so they broke away from Uruk.
而且从乌鲁克分离。
And this led to tension and
这导致了紧张与
conflict and maybe sometimes even outright warfare.
冲突与...
But please remember, during this time,
但请记得，在此时，乌鲁克的概念…
the idea of the Uruk, the Uruk civilization, was massive warfare that
...
we would see during the Greek and Roman periods.
我们将在希腊与罗马时期看到它。
It's still pretty absent. There's conflict.
它仍然很少见。发生了冲突。
It's short -term.
...
And they have conflicts in order to resolve
like territorial disputes or trade disputes.
像领土争端或贸易争端。
But they're not trying to wipe each other out.
但他们并未尝试互相消灭。
One of the great mysteries is
...
where the Sumerians come from.
We have this problem because when
...
we discovered cuneiform, and we translated the Sumerian language,
我们发现楔形文字，并把苏美尔语翻译出来，
we discovered the spoken language is
我们发现了语言的方言，
very different from the surrounding regions
翻译…
who spoke something called a Semitic language.
谁说过一种叫做塞米特语的语言。
So the languages spoken in the area are part of a Semitic language group.
塞尔语里有个语种，塞尔语里…
But Sumerian is not part of that group.
此时…
There's not enough similarities.
有点儿…
Also, there is no other language
...
like Sumerian in the world.
Okay? It's what is called a language isolate.
OK? 这就是…
It is unique.
...
And so this has puzzled scholars
for decades. And quite honestly,
for de ... …
no one knows why this is the case.
...
Okay? No one knows. There are different theories.
OK? 这…
One theory is the Sumerian people are people
...
who came from Anatolia and settled in the Middle East. And they were not the only ones who
settled in the dataset due to due due due due due due
?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? … …… … … ?? … ? ? … … {
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
...
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
由于...
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due people who
由于...
believe the Sumerians are people
相信萨尔马尔人是从印度河谷来的人
who came from the Indus Valley.
相信萨尔玛尔人…
Okay, we'll talk about the Indus Valley next class,
好的，接下来一节课我们来讲Indus河流域...
but all you need to know is the Indus Valley,
...
it is a very advanced civilization,
它是一个非常先进的文明，
it's very large, five million people, and it covers three
它大约五百万人口，且覆盖三
major areas, Afghanistan, Pakistan, and northwest India.
主要地区包括阿富格尼亚、巴基斯坦和西北印度。
It is larger than Egypt
主要地区是大于埃及
and Mesopotamia combined.
...
Okay, so people believe that
the Indus Valley sent
印古斯河谷派出殖民到美索波特米亚，
a colony to Mesopotamia,
它在约里克发现之，
which found it in Yorick, and it makes sense because
它之所作之可见
it's actually pretty easy to get
它是大于埃及的...
from Indus Valley to Yorick because of the Arabian Sea.
...
Okay, so
these are the different theories, but then there's another theory,
这些是不同的理论，但随后又出现了另一种理论。
okay, which I think makes the most sense, which is this.
好的，我认为最合适的就是这一个。
Sumerian is a Creole language.
苏美尔语是克里奥语。
It was invented by a
它是由...
melting pot of cultures and languages,
它的...
and it's very similar to the Mandarin we speak today,
...
right, where Mandarin didn't exist,
右边，汉语还没出现时，
but because you had so
但因你们有多种
many different cultures coming to the palace,
多种…
they had to create their own language in order to communicate with each other.
...
And we call that language today Mandarin.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, so why do I think
...
this idea makes the most sense?
这个想法最有道理吗？
And again, just to be absolutely clear, no one knows,
再一次，先把它说清楚：我方…
and we'll probably never know the answer, but I believe that Sumerian is a Creole language.
…
This theory makes the most sense because of this.
这个理论最有道理，因为这个。
Why was Yorick able to develop into the first city?
为什么Yorick能发展成第一个城市？
What makes it special? The answer is this.
它的答案是这…
It is at the center of the world.
它位于世界中心。
Okay, so let me explain.
好的，我来解释一下。
From Yorick, you're able to access the Indus Valley.
从约里克可以到达印度河谷。
You're able to access the Arabian Desert.
你可以进入阿拉伯沙漠。
You're able to go north to Anatolia and the Zagreus Mountains, okay.
你可以去北方的安塔利亚和扎格雷斯山脉，好的。
And these civilizations we know traded with each other
我们知道这几种文明相互交流。
due to due due due due due due
due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
...
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
...
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
That explains why Europe was able to prosper
那就好啦！
so fast, because it's the center of the world.
...
To get anywhere, you have to go for your Earth, okay?
316. 先到达里程里程??
But if that's the case, if it's a trading center of the world,
?
it makes sense for it to be also a multicultural
...
and
multilingual community of people, right?
多语言的群体，没错！
Because these traders from Arabia,
因为这几位来自阿拉伯的商人
Anatolia, the Zagos Mountains, also let's not forget about the Yemeni,
安塔利亚，佐格斯山脉，...
okay, who are up here in the steppes.
...
They also trade with these people.
他们也与这些人进行贸易。
People from the Innis Valley, it makes sense for them to come together in a training community
来自伊尼斯河谷的人民，先前已成就好吧！
and develop their own language and their own culture, which eventually spreads.
...
Also, because this is a melting pot, it's really an immigrant culture,
they're able to bring the most advanced ideas from all around the world
...
and combine them together, which
creates new inventions like writing,
创造新的发明如文字，
like legal system, like mathematics,
像 … … … … … … … … … … … ... … … … … … … … … … … ...
like astronomy, okay?
...
And that's why Samaria became the cradle of civilization,
because of the meeting place of the world's cultures
...
and ideas.
And because of the very instability of the environment,
336. 先后??
okay, meaning they have to tame the Tigris and Euphrates,
and because they were always threatened by outside enemies,
...
they had to develop a new culture,
他们需要发展新的文化，
a new mythology based on struggle, right?
他们需要发展新的神话，基于斗争的...
The Egyptians can afford to be passive and fatalistic.
埃及人可有闲暇去做被动与命运的事。
Let the gods decide.
让神来决定吧。
But because this is an immigrant community, they have to focus on struggle and attack. Yeah,
但因这是一群移民，必须聚焦于斗争与攻击。
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
嗯，...
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
...
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
对
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah
...
yeah with Mesopotamian
mythology to show how the geographic
...
and cultural difference translates into the mythology,
the shared reality of the people, okay?
...
So let's look at Egypt first.
All right, so again, Egypt, it's a very ancient civilization,
好的，回到埃及，它是个古老的文明
and their mythology is extremely complex.
它的神话非常复杂。
They have different versions of the same stories, okay?
他们有不同版本的同一故事，OK?
But I'm gonna give you the generalization,
...
which will be useful for our purposes, okay?
哪会对我们有用，好的？
So let's look at Egypt. So, and then we'll look at Mesopotamia.
先看埃及吧，先后会去看中东
Okay, Egypt. Egypt believed the first god was Ra,
OK? 先前的...??
okay? There are other gods
?
who they believed to be the first god, like Atum and Amon, okay?
谁是他们认为的第一位神，像是个…??
But let's just say the first god is Ra, who is a sun god.
...??
He comes to our world, and
他来到我们的世界，随后...
he creates life, okay?
他人…
He basically gives life to everything, okay?
他基本把生命赋予万物，好的？
Including humans.
包括人类。
And as such, we worship him.
于是我们便把它当作…
But eventually, we start to become misguided,
但最终我们开始误入歧途，
and we start to worship. And we start to worship another god, a false god.
并且开始把它们给我方…?】?】?】?】?】??】?】??】?】????】?????】??????????????????????????????????????????】?????】?……??…??……………………………………………………………………???????????????{
Ra becomes angry and kills many of us.
]}We need to translate cues 370-372. Provide Chinese subtitles. Use line breaks appropriately. Provide JSON array with three translations. Let's craft translations. Cue 370:
But after he kills many of us, he has tremendous regret,
但他在杀了许多人后，...
and he decides his time is up.
...
He should give his throne to someone else, okay?
And this other god becomes Osiris.
...
Osiris is a great god, because he gives people civilization,
Osiris is a great god, becausehe gives people civilization,
which includes cities, which includes the pyramids,
which includes writing, okay?
写作...
So it's Osiris who gives us civilization.
...
Now here's a brother named Set.
And Set is very jealous of the fact
...
that Osiris is worshiped by the people.
那一刻...
So he plots to usurp the throne from Osiris.
...
So what he does is this. He builds a sarcophagus, a tomb, okay?
He presents to Osiris and says,
Osiris, my great king,
...
this sarcophagus is the most beautiful
and comfortable sarcophagus in the world.
舒适的石棺在世界上。
You will love lying in here.
你会在此处打工
And Osiris is like, oh, that's interesting.
我想要点儿...??
Let me try. So
?
Osiris gets into the sarcophagus,
奥西里斯进入石棺
and Set closes it forever, okay?
奥西里斯进入石棺后，塞特关闭了它
Then he kills Osiris and dismembers his body.
然后他杀了奥西里斯并把他的身体分成几块。
Osiris has a wife, Isis, and when
奥西里斯有一个妻子，...
he hears about the death of her husband,
...
she looks for his body
and assembles it together.
and assembles ittogether.
But she can't find the head. And then
...
Osiris becomes the god of the underworld, okay?
Osiris becomes the godof the underworld, okay?
After Osiris is reassembled,
After Osiris isreassembled,
he impregnates Isis.
他在 里斯里 … ?? …?? … ?? … …
They have a son named Horus.
...
Horus eventually grows up, and he's angered by the fact
霍鲁斯最终长大，随后又把它…
that his uncle, Set, has usurped the throne.
霍尔斯…
He's going to usurp his throne, okay?
他要篡夺王位，行吗？
So the two are going to battle.
于是两人相互交战。
And the gods, who judge all, tell them
和神们，判定一切的神们，告诉他们：他们要互相对决，行吗？
they have to challenge each other to a duel, okay?
So they have a series of duels.
411: 1/2? 2? ...??? ……………………………………………………………??…………??…………………………………………………………………...???…………
One duel is they both turn into hippopotamus,
]}We need to produce JSON with translations array of two strings: for cues411 and 412. Use simplified Chinese. Use terms. Let's translate: cue 411:
and they try to stay in the river for the longest time possible.
他把他母亲伊西斯说给他，...
Horus sees this as an opportunity to kill, you know, Set.
...
He tells his mother, Isis, while Set is distracted,
他把母亲伊西斯说给他，...
while he's a hippopotamus, take a spear and kill him.
...
And Isis agrees. But when
和伊西斯同意。但当她试图击杀塞特时，...
she tries to kill Set,
她在尝试击杀塞特时...
she is paralyzed with fear, and she fails.
?
Horus, in anger, strikes,
胡鲁斯愤怒之下，挥手击打，去掉她母亲的头！
beheads her mother.
胡胡...??
He doesn't kill her, but she loses her head.
...
That's how angry he is, okay?
那就是他那时的那点儿很大??
So Isis and Horus continue their challenge.
...??
Eventually, Set decides to poison Horus.
...
But before he can do so, Horus first poisons him.
但在他行动之前，胡鲁斯先把他给了个点儿！
Okay? Then Horus becomes king, and
OK? 先后??
he gives Egypt the institution of kingship.
...
So every pharaoh is a direct descendant of Horus,
所以每位法老都是霍鲁斯的直系后裔，或是霍鲁斯的另一重生，好的？
or another reincarnation of Horus, okay?
或者说是霍鲁斯的另一重生，好的？
That is the Egyptian situation.
...
Egyptian myth of creation.
Now, the Mesopotamians, okay,
现在，米塞普特米安人们...??
they have a different myth of creation called the Enuma Elesh,
?
from up high.
从高处开始。
Okay? The Enuma Elesh.
好的？ 这就是“恩乌玛·埃勒什”
And this is the story of the Enuma Elesh.
和这就是恩乌玛·埃勒什的故事。
There are two gods.
有两个神。
The first god is Tiamat,
第一个神是提亚玛特，
who is basically salt water, okay?
who is basicallysalt water, okay?
Then you have Apsu, who is fresh water.
然后有阿普苏，...
The two great gods get together,
...??…????????????????????? ！
and they give birth to other gods, okay?
他们给了另一个神的诞生，好的？
They're children. These gods then give birth to other gods, okay?
他们的孩子们又给了另一个神的诞生，好的？
Eventually, Apsu gets annoyed with his children
最终，阿普苏因孩子们的声音而发作了
because children are loud, and he can't sleep.
最终的阿普苏…
So he resolves to kill all his children and...
447. 之所以...
bring peace to the world.
...????...???
Tiamat finds out about Apsu's diabolical plan,
Tiamat finds out aboutApsu's diabolical plan,
and he warns, she warns her children.
他发出声响，随后又给了另一个神的诞生，好的？
The gods get together, and they kill Apsu.
他发出声响…
Tiamat is enraged by the death of her consort,
and she resolves to raise a great army
...
and destroy her children, okay?
The gods get together, and
翻译：...
they elect Marduk,
who is the son of the god.
翻译：...
So he's basically a third -generation god, okay?
...
They elect Marduk to lead them in battle against Tiamat,
okay? So you have these two massive armies converging against each other,
好的，接下来是两支大军相互冲向，...??
and then Tiamat turns into a huge water serpent
]}We need to translate cues 460 and 461. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure Chinese natural. Let's translate: cue 460:
and challenges Marduk to a duel.
和他发起了双重之战。
They fight, okay?
他们相互相冲冲…??
Marduk unleashes whirlwinds,
...
into the mouth of Tiamat,
???
and that sort of like, dizzies her, and then Marduk strikes her down.
...
After he kills her,
she uses her body to create the world.
她用身体创造世界。
She uses half of her body to create the sky, and
她用半个身体创造天空
she uses another half of the body to create the continents, okay?
她用另一半身体去生成地球。
He creates the moons, and he creates the stars.
他创造了月亮和星星。
He creates the entire universe, basically, from the body of Tiamat.
他从Tiamat的身体里创造了整个宇宙。
After that,
]}
the gods all decide to rest in peace,
神们决定安静下来，
but they need people to take care of them.
神们决定休息，随后需要人来照料。
They need people to watch the land,
他们需要人来守护土地，农耕耕耕。
to farm and till the land.
他们需要人来守护土地，农耕耕耙。
So they create humans as their slaves, okay?
So they...??
Humans. Humans.
...
And that's how the Enem -Elish ends,
安啦，埃尔希尔结束了。
okay? Each city has...
每个城市都有…
Each city has its own god, and the humans in that city must revere
每个城市都有自己的神，城市里的人们必须敬拜并为之作祷。
and take care of that god to be their slave for all of eternity,
每个城市都有自己的神，城市里的人们必需敬拜并为之作祷
okay? All right,
好吧，全部都好！
so as you can see right away,
可见一大批…??
there are massive differences between
]}?????????????????????????????????? [??]???????????? [??..??..??..??..??????..??..?????..???…??…????????…??..??..……??…??..??..……………??…..??…..…..??..??..???..……..………..??…..??..??..?????..??..………………??…..……..…..??…..??……..??..??……..??....……..??…....……..??……..??…..???……..??..
Egyptian mythology and Mesopotamian mythology,
...
okay?
The first major difference
...
is the gods are benevolent,
是的，神们是个好事！
right? The gods give us everything.
...
We just sit back, and the gods will give us light.
They will give us civilization. They will give us kingship.
他们会给我们文明。它们会给我们王位。
They will give us the pyramids. So
他们会给我们金字塔。于是...
all we have to do is respect and revere and worship the gods.
我们只需做的就是给神们敬礼、敬服、再给他们打点儿…
We humans don't need to participate in the order of things.
我们人类不必参与事物的秩序。
But, in the Enem -Elish, we find out that gods
但在《恩尼玛尔》里，神们才是…
are extremely violent,
...
and they demand our servitude.
They are our masters, okay? So
...
we must constantly work
to please the gods.
为了取悦神明
That's one major difference. Second major difference is, as you can see,
这是一个大差异点。第二个大差异点是…
from the Egyptian mythology,
从古埃及的神话中
the main virtues of the gods are, due due due
...
due due due due due due
???
due due due due due due due due due due due due
]}We need to translate cues 506 and 507. They are
due due due due due due due
due due due duedue due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
?
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
???
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
???
due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due due
And this is no different from China, right?
514. 这就是中国的那一段，没错吧？
Because remember in China, we have something called Shunzi Bingfa,
515. 先前记得有个“先前”????
the art of war by Shunzi.
516. 先前的战争艺术
That is a manual on palace intrigue, right?
517. 那个…??
How to trick other people.
如何用来回到的？
It's not a manual on how to go to war.
...
Okay? But
好的？但
here, the value
...
that
is most prominent in Mesopotamia
在美索不太显著
is bravery or strength.
是勇气或强度。
Okay, not cleverness.
好的，不是机巧。
There's no trickery going on.
这里有个空格。
It's just pure power, pure bravery.
它只是纯粘力，纯勇气。
Okay? And
]}We need to translate cues 527 and 528. The translation should be natural Simplified Chinese. Use preferred terms. The cues: [527] It's just pure power,pure bravery. [528] Okay? And. We need to produce JSON with translations array. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Let's translate:
the third major difference is in Egypt,
它只是纯粘力，纯勇气。
they believe the gods.
好？】】
Are helping each other.
它只是纯粘力，纯勇气。
Okay, they build on top of each other's legacy.
好？】
That's what progress is.
它只是纯粘力，纯勇气。
That's what improvement is.
好？】】
But in Mesopotamia, they believe in something called creative destruction.
??
Which is to say, in order to create something new,
哪怕是为了创造新事物，你需要先行销旧的
you must destroy the old.
哪怕…??
Okay? Tiamat represents the old.
好的？提亚玛特代表旧的。
Therefore, she must be destroyed.
好的，...】
And from the old, you can.
从旧事物中，你可以……
Okay? Build a new civilization.
好吧，先建造新建造
But you must first destroy the old.
但你先得先销旧
And conflict is a source of creativity.
冲突是个好造造
Okay, does that make sense?
好的，这有道理吗？
And again, they have these two different mythologies,
再一次，他们有两种不同的神话，
because they're reflecting the shared reality of the different geographies
因为它们反映了不同地理的共同现实
and history. Okay?
因为它们的回顾回到地理的古典回顾
So, they're both in the same place. Any questions so far?
所以，二者都在同一地点。 先前有问？
Before I continue?
在前先？
Are you clear? Okay, great.
]}We need to translate cue [550]
Great. Okay. All right. Let's continue. All right.
好的。好的。我们继续。
Okay. So, both Egypt
...
and both Mesopotamia,
和两者都在古巴比伦，
they are in a struggle to prove their mythologies are the best.
他们在争夺证明自己的神话是最好的。
Okay? The reason why is, remember that
好的？原因在于，记得那时
this is a time when
OK? 记得那时…
all these civilizations are trading with each other.
所有这些文明彼此之间进行贸易。
But also what's important to understand is,
把...??
there's a lot of migration going on.
有很多迁移正在进行。
And people have a choice.
而人们有选择。
If you're not happy here, you can always move somewhere else.
如果你不满意这里，可以随时搬到别处。
Okay? There isn't any idea of like nation or culture or race.
好的？这里有个别名：…
People have autonomy.
人们拥有自主权。
Okay? So, you need to constantly prove that
好的，...
your civilization is the best to attract people,
你的文明是最能吸引人们的，
which provides the labor to drive your civilization.
它给了劳动力，来推动你的文明。
Right? So,
?
the Egyptians created something called the pyramids.
埃及人创造了一个叫做金字塔的东西。
The pyramids. To show the people around them,
金字塔是给给我方的，来给我方…
we are favored by the gods.
先前…
Because they're the ones who are favored. Because it's only the gods who
因为...??
could inspire us to build the pyramids.
]}We need to translate cues 571-573. Provide translations array with 3 strings. Use Chinese terms. Let's translate each cue line by line. Cue 571:
Okay? So now,
. Actually cue 571 is:
the people in Mesopotamia have a problem.
在中东有个…
Because how do you compete against the pyramids?
...
Right? I mean, at first they tried.
They created things called the ziggurats.
在中东有个问题。
The ziggurats, which are temples to house the gods.
它们的神话故事…
Okay? But then, they did something that was completely different.
好的，先前…
And which made them immortal.
它们使他们成为不朽者。
Just as the pyramids made Egyptians immortal.
正如古埃及的古塔使得古埃及人们…
They created something called the Epic of Gilgamesh.
那时…
And today,
和…
we celebrate the Epic of Gilgamesh as
我们…
the first work of world literature.
...
Okay? So,
好的？那么，
let me first explain the plot of the Epic of Gilgamesh.
先给我来个咱们的...
And show you how it works.
...
How it reflects Mesopotamian culture and values.
如何反映……马斯波特米亚文化与…
And then explain the meaning of it.
…………………
So, the Epic of Gilgamesh.
………………
So, there was a king of Uruk.
所以，乌鲁克有一位国王。
Okay? The first city.
好的？第一座城市。
Uruk. And he's the king of the first city.
乌鲁克。并且是第一座城市的国王。
And he's a demigod.
他是半神。
Okay? He's huge.
好的？他很大。
He's a giant. And he's very brave.
他是巨人，且很勇敢。
The first city. The problem is, even
第一座城市。问题在于，已建成的乌鲁克城。
though he's built this great city, Uruk.
高墙，繁荣的土地。
High walls. Prosperous land.
Advanced civilization. He gets bored very quickly.
高级文明。他很快就会感到无聊。
And he starts to bully the people around him.
他开始了咬咬的咬咬。
So, he sees young men.
他又看见了年轻人
He challenges them to a fight.
他挑战他们进行一场战斗。
And he beats them up. Okay? He's a bully.
他把他打败了。好吧？又是个咬咬。
He also rapes all the young women in Uruk.
他又在乌拉克里又打了个咬咂
And this drives their parents to pray to the gods for relief.
并且把它们的父亲们给了个别名？
So, the gods decide to create
...
an equal to Gilgamesh.
And his name is Enkidu. Enkidu.
他的名字叫恩基杜。恩基杜。
And Enkidu is made of clay.
恩基杜由泥土制成。
The two fight.
两人相互搏斗。
And even though Gilgamesh defeats Enkidu in battle.
并且即使吉尔伽美什在战斗中击败恩基杜。
He's defeated. Gilgamesh is happy
他已击败。吉尔伽美什很高兴。
because he thinks he's found a good friend.
因为他能在此时给他一位好朋友。
Someone who is equal. Who he can share adventures with.
一个与之相等的人。可以与他共享冒险的人。
So, the two become great friends.
于是两人成为了大朋友。
The best of friends. They go on these adventures together.
最好的朋友。他们一起去冒险。
And these adventures are tremendous challenges.
并且...
For example, they challenge gods to battle.
...
And at first they're afraid.
But through their friendship and through their bravery.
但通过他们的友谊与勇气。
They're able to triumph in the end.
他们最终能获胜。
There's a god named Ishtar.
有一个名为伊什塔尔的神。
And she falls in love with Gilgamesh because he's so heroic.
625. 译文1
But Gilgamesh rebuffs Ishtar.
625. 1?
Because Gilgamesh basically knows
...
that Ishtar wants to turn him into her sex slave.
伊什塔尔想把他变成自己的性奴隶。
He doesn't want that. He wants his freedom.
他不想这样，他想要自由。
He wants to prove he's a great hero.
他想证明自己是个伟大的英雄。
Ishtar feels rejected.
伊什塔尔感到被拒绝。
Feels ashamed. So, she says.
伊什塔尔感到...
She sends someone called the Bull of Heaven to destroy Uruk.
其...
Gilgamesh and Enkidu fight the Bull of Heaven.
吉尔伽美什与恩基杜战斗天之公牛。
And they kill this great bull.
他们杀死这只大公牛。
The gods now are really pissed off at Gilgamesh and Enkidu.
神们此时已把吉尔伽美什与恩基杜逼得很激动。
And they decide that Enkidu must die.
翻译1
So, they inflict a disease on Enkidu.
翻译2
Which kills him. At this point,
翻译句
Gilgamesh is heartbroken.
吉尔伽美什心碎了。
He's lost his best friend.
他已失去最好的朋友。
At the same time, he knows death is waiting for him.
与此同时，他知道自己正等待着死亡。
He has all these accomplishments.
他拥有这些成就。
He's a great king. He's built this great city.
他是个大王，建造了这座大城。
But eventually he must die.
但他最终会去世。
And he does not want to die. He fears death.
他不想死，怕死。
So, he hears about this immortal man.
他听见了那位久已久的古人。
This man who has lived forever.
这位古人已久已久。”
And who will live forever. And he decides to seek him out.
他决定去寻找他。
On his journey. He has to overcome many hurdles.
他在旅途中要经历许多的事。
And along the journey. Along the journey, everyone implores him.
在旅途中，大家都向他请示。
Gilgamesh, give up this vain project.
吉尔伽美什，放弃这空无的项目。
Immortality is for the gods.
不久的古人已久已久。
We are humans. We must die.
我们是人类，回到回到。”
That's what makes us different from the gods.
那就是我们与神不同的地方。
Enjoy your life.
享 好 时 刻 ！
Drink. Be merry.
喝 好 喝 ！
But Gilgamesh refuses to turn back.
但吉尔伽美什不回到回到。
And he insists.
又是个别的??
On continuing on his journey.
继续…
Eventually, he finds this immortal man.
最终，他找到了这位不朽之人。
Who explains to him.
他向他解释。
He was made immortal.
他被赋予不朽。
Because he survived the great flood.
因为他在大洪水中幸存。
The gods created humans.
神们创造了人类。
But the humans became too loud.
但人类发出声响，已足够响亮。
For the gods. So the gods resolved to kill them.
为神们。于是神们决定杀死他们。
But this man.
但这位人。
This one man was favored.
这位人被选中。
By one god. So he was told about this plot.
由一位神所说。于是他得知此计。
And he built a boat.
他建造船只。
And put a lot of animals in the boat.
船只里装满了许多动物。
In order to escape.
为了逃脱
And this is the basis of the story of the north's flood.
这就是北方洪水的故事基础。
In the bible. Okay. After the flood receded.
在圣经中。好，回到洪水后
This man came down.
这位人降临。
And built an altar. To worship the gods.
他建造祭坛。以祭神。
The gods felt regret for what they did.
神们为所作而感到愣。
So to compensate.
于是补偿。
They promised. Never to do this again.
他们已承诺。再也不再做此事。
To never destroy humanity again.
再不再把人类 …
And also. They grant this man immortality.
又是…
Okay. So.
好吧…
But this is just a one off.
But this is justa one off.
The gods would never do this again.
神们再也不会这样做了。
And so the man tells Gilgamesh.
于是，男人向吉尔伽美什说。
The search for immortality.
寻找神的永生之旅。
It's pointless. Just go home.
它没什么用。直接回家吧。
But Gilgamesh refuses to give up.
但吉尔伽美什不愿意回去。
So the man challenges Gilgamesh.
于是，男人向吉尔伽美什发起挑战。
To not sleep for seven days.
不睡七天
Seven nights and six days.
七夜六日
Sorry. Six days and seven.
抱歉，六天七夜
Six nights and seven days.
六夜七天
Okay. Gilgamesh tries.
好的，吉尔伽美什尝试着
But he can't do it. So it's all futile.
他还没能做出来，才是回去的回归
And then he goes home. But the moment he goes home.
然后他回到家里。可是回到家时的那一刻。
He has an epiphany. He sees the great walls of Urich.
他有一个灵感，看到大墙的古里奇。
He sees the people happy in Urich.
他在古里奇看到人们的喜悦。
And he realizes. This is what immortality is.
翻译1
Immortality is. Not living forever.
翻译译2
Immortality is.
翻译译3
To be remembered.
被记住
By the people who love you.
由...
So the irony of all this is.
...
He goes on this search for immortality.
他踏上寻找不朽之旅程。
He fails. But because he goes on this search.
他失败了，但因其踏上了旅程。
Because he goes on this quest.
因为他踏上了这场旅程。
He becomes immortal. Because his story.
他变成不朽。因为他的故事。
His struggle. His struggle. Is remembered
他的斗争。斗争??
and celebrated by the people in the Epic of Gilgamesh.
Okay. So this is a reflection of the values of Mesopotamia.
好的。于是这就是古巴比伦的价值观反映。
The point is in the achievement.
点在于此刻的成就。
The point is not in the victory.
点在于此刻的成就…
The point is in the exploration.
点在于探索。
The point is in the struggle.
点在于斗争。
And that's why the Mesopotamians were so innovative.
于是古巴比伦人如此创新。
But that's also why they went to war with each other all the time.
...
And this is the beginning of the idea of literature,
where
...
memories can be shaped in such a way
记忆可在此处…
that becomes so beautiful that
...
it becomes implanted in the minds of others for centuries,
centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries,
centuries...
centuries, centuries, centuries,
?
centuries,
centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries,
翻译1
centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries,
]}
centuries, centuries, centuries, centuries,
翻译1
centuries, centuries, Egypt.
???
But the Epic of Gilgamesh is also a testament to the tremendous creativity of
]}We need to translate cues 730-732. Provide array of translations in order. Let's translate each line into Simplified Chinese, following guidelines. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use natural phrase breaks. Let's produce translations: 730:
that civilization. And if you think about it, the Epic of Gilgamesh was written
， but we need Chinesetranslation. The cue:
because it is in a dialectic with the pyramids, right?
...
The Epic of Gilgamesh is also saying to the pyramids,
第734行的译文
immortality it is an illusion.
第735行的译文
Eventually these pyramids will collapse.
最终...
For the Pharaoh to seek immortality is an illusion.
...
What matters is for the Pharaoh to look after the well -being of his people here
什么才是...
and now because that's why he will be loved and remembered for eternity.
...
He will die if
他会在...
his people die. But
...
if your people live on
如果你的人们在...
because of your contributions, then you'll remember forever.
因为...
You'll become immortal. Right?
你将变成不朽的...
And that's the story of Gilgamesh.
...
Any questions?
任何问题？
Is this all pretty clear?
这全都很清楚吗？
Okay. Alright. So
好的。好的。于是
I will make a final point about these stories,
我会在这些故事里再说一点点。
okay? Within these stories,
在这几句里...
we can see the evolution of the world.
我们可以看到世界的演变。
Of societies over time.
社会的演变随时间而变。
Okay? So let's go back to the story of the Enuma Elesh.
好的？我们回到Enuma Eleh的故事。”
So, remember, Tiamat and Apsu create the world.
所以，记住，提亚玛特与阿普苏创造了世界。
That's the first story.
那是第一条故事。
Then, the gods are created, okay?
然后，神们就算好了。”
And then they inhabit the world, that second story.
然后他们居住在世界里，那第二个故事。
And then, Tiamat and Marduk go to war.
然后，塔伊玛特与马尔杜克去战斗。
And then, from the victory of this war, before Marduk creates the universe.
然后，马尔杜克胜利后，先前先前…
So basically we're seeing three different mythologies embedded within this mythology,
所以我们大致看到三种不同的神话嵌入在此神话里。
which gives us the idea of social change and evolution,
它们给了我方位的后期…
Mesopenia, at this time.
其后…
The first story is Tiamat.
第一段故事是塔伊玛特。
Who is Tiamat? She's the mother goddess.
谁是塔伊玛特？她是母神。
She's the one who gives life.
她是给出发的那位。
So this shows Mesopenia as an agricultural society.
所以这显示了美索波尼亚作为农业社会。
Then you have the emergence of the gods,
然后是...??
which the urban people would celebrate.
...
And then finally you have the battle between Tiamat and Marduk.
然后终于出现了塔伊玛特与马尔杜克之间的战斗。
And this shows the battle between the old society with the new society,
这显示了旧社会与新社会之间的战斗，好的？
okay? The urban and the agricultural.
The agricultural, it is egalitarian,
农业社会是平等的，它是个好好的！
it is peaceful.
城市化的...??
The urban is patriarchal, right?
So why, how do we explain,
...
or how do you justify the transition from an equal society to a patriarchy?
The answer is this. The answer is embedded in the mythology, right?
...
Tiamat represents chaos.
塔伊玛特代表混沌。
Marduk represents order.
马尔杜克代表着名古。
So even though we are letting go of the old, we're destroying the old,
...
it's to create a more peaceful, peaceful and orderly world.
So remember, Tiamat is the water serpent.
记住，塔伊玛特就是水蛇。
And for the longest time,
而已久的时间里，
we believe the water serpent to represent life
我们相信水蛇代表着生命与神性。
and divinity.
我们相信水蛇是个别名
Why? Because if you think about it,
为什么？因为如果你想一想，
the water serpent looks like the river.
水河河河...
And the river is the basis of all civilization, right?
河流是所有文明的基础，对吧？
So, and this is true for most civilizations.
所以，河流也好好…
In China, what do we call the water serpent?
在中国，我们把水蛇称作什么？
What do we call the water serpent in China?
在中国，水蛇叫什么？
Long, right?
长吗？
The problem is the river floods.
河流的水位很高。
And if you flood too much, you destroy civilization.
如果你过度泛滇，便可把文明消灭。
So it's chaotic, okay?
好吧，先前后两句的前后两句？
And that's why it's important to have a patriarchy
...
or an urban elite, because they can help us,
command us, to create irrigation,
...
to build walls, which
建造墙壁，...
will tame the river and the water serpent.
...
Okay, does that make sense?
Okay, does thatmake sense?
So within this mythology,
在这段神话中，
we are seeing the evolution
我们看到社会从平等到父系的演变。
of society from an egalitarian one to a patriarchy,
okay? Yeah,
好的，...
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
...
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
Right, because remember,
好的，记得吧，
the story starts with the king going on all these adventures.
故事开始时，王子去往里去的…
Okay, the story ends with the king coming back
好的…
and recognizing what matters is the well -being of his people.
好的，...
And for that, you need a bureaucracy to manage everyday affairs.
? ? …… …… We need to translate cues 811-813. Provide JSON translations array. Each string may have newline. Let's translate: cue 811:
Okay? And so this represents,
， actually text:
you can interpret this as
...
representing the beginning of a bureaucratic elite,
which will help the king order the world in a way
...
that brings more stability and prosperity to the people.
那带来更多稳定与繁荣给人民。
Okay? But first, the king must recognize his own hubris.
好的，先前先...??...???????
He must become humble.
...
So the great fear of the Mesopotamians is their king will become like a pharaoh
于是，古巴比伦人对他们的王的巨大恐惧是：他会像巴比伦王一样，像…
who will channel all resources to build this monument,
…………………
which will create inequality, corruption, and
………后…
waste in society, which
在社会中浪费，随后将导致旱季大规模的痛苦。
will lead to massive suffering during times of drought.
好的？好的！
Okay? Okay.
Okay, any questions?
好的，任何问题吗？
Yeah.
是的！
好的！
Yeah. Yeah.
是的！是的！
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. that would change over time.
是的！是的！是的！是的！那会变成时间的。”
The thing about Sumeria is
...
because it's trading and because there are different city -states,
this becomes a hotbed of innovation
...
because if one city -state creates a really good irrigation system,
因为如果一个城邦建立了非常好的灌溉系统，另一个城邦就能很容易地复制它。
another city -state could just copy it really easily.
因为如果一个城邦有好好的灌溕系统，另一城邦就能很容易地复制。”
Does that make sense?
那算得了？
Any more questions?
还有什么问题吗？
Okay. Okay, so next class,
好的，接下来一节课...
we'll discuss the Indus Valley civilization,
好的，接下来...
okay? And the Indus Valley civilization,
好的？接着说印度河谷文明，
if we just use the analysis we did today, where basically geography is destiny,
?
you would think the Indus Valley civilization is very much like the Egyptian civilization
你会认为印度河谷文明很像埃及文明
where you have a monarchy, you have centralized authority,
你会想到印度河谷文明很像埃及文明
where they build these great monuments, okay?
在他们建造这些宏伟的纪念碑时，好吗？
The irony is when
当...
you look at the Indus Valley civilization, and it's a huge, huge civilization,
你看印度河谷文明，它是一个巨大的文明，
they have very advanced technology.
它们拥有非常先进的技术。
They have these big cities that are very well designed.
他们有这些大城市，设计得很完善。
They have plumbing, they have sanitation.
他们有管道，排水系统。
They even have air conditioning. They have these towers.
他们还可以装有空调，空调也有。
That sort of like trap hot air.
...
People live for a very long time.
人们寿命很长。
I think over half of the population will live past 55,
我想大约一半人口会活到55岁以上，
which is incredible, which is an incredible achievement.
这很惊人，且是个很好的成绩。
But what is startling about the civilization,
...
the Indus Valley civilization is, it's peaceful and it's egalitarian.
So it's a complete mystery as to why they're
...
so different from the other civilizations.
不同于其他文明。
So, the reason why they're so different is because they're so different from Egypt and Mesopotamia, okay, because again, Egypt, it's a centralized empire.
所以，原因是因为它们与埃及和美索不太相同，先后…
Mesopotamia is always at war.
...
So, next class,
好的，下一节课，
we will look at the Indus Valley civilization
我们来看看印度河谷文明，
and try to resolve the paradox as to why it is advanced,
并且以此来解开它的...
prosperous, but at the same time, peaceful and egalitarian.
...